I have been really looking forward to
today's talk because we are going to be
talking about race and racism in higher
education. And to me this topic is
really fitting for the series because my
frustrations
about racism and the lack of black,
Asian, and minority ethnic researchers
in physics are what inspired me to start
the challenges and change of series. And
I'm so excited to be able to introduce
our speaker for today, Dr. Jason Arday.
He is an assistant professor in
sociology at Durham University, and he
is a leading expert on the study of race
and education.
Now, I first came across Jason's work in
a BBC news article about the lack of PhD
funding awarded to black students in the
UK, and I knew we here at Oxford Physics
needed to hear about his research and
see what we can learn from it and how we
can be better.
He's done extensive work on the
importance of decolonizing the
curriculum, on how racism persists in
higher education, and how racism affects
the mental health of black, Asian, and
minority ethnic researchers. His work is
so important for us all regardless of
our research interests, and I think it's
incredibly fitting for the series. And
I'm so happy he agreed to come and talk
to us today. So, Jason, welcome, albeit
virtually, to the Oxford Physics
Department, and thank you so much, and
I'm so excited to hear from you.
Uh thank you so so much, Alex, and I
can't tell you how much
how much it means to be here. And you
know, the great thing about doing this
work is that you get to meet some pretty
cool people, and I would hold you very
highly amongst them. So, just thank you
so much for having me here. It really
means a lot. Massive thanks
to Catherine and to Anna who are doing a
lot of stuff behind the scenes as well.
And probably most importantly, good
afternoon, everyone. How's everyone
keeping? Is everyone well?
I guess I can't tell cuz I can't see
everyone, but I'm just hoping that
everyone's okay. So,
that's good. Thanks, Anna. Anna, that's
good.
Um so,
I mean, we're in a
interesting situation right now. Uh I
think there are several things
that kind of come to mind when we think
of race and racism institutionally,
structurally, but particularly within
higher education.
And I think the thing that comes to mind
at the moment or the word that I kind of
think about with all of
these kind of tenants associated with
racism
and even, you know, the sad murder of
Sarah Everard is vigilance.
At the moment, I think vigilance is the
issue. I think there's been a
complacency
that's become commonplace.
It's become part of the normal orthodoxy
in terms of how we socialize, how we
integrate in society, where people
are increasingly becoming victimized,
demonized, they're having their lives
placed at risk.
And I think for across the intersection,
this is troubling. I think when we think
specifically about race and racism and
we think about
how intersection works and how for a
person of color, how they traverse
society
whilst navigating issues around class,
sexuality gender, race, obviously
disability,
religion.
We we kind of see all of those we kind
of see it as almost
this kind of, I guess, in many respects
a process that kind of scaffolds on top
of one of the other and I think what's
been increasingly hard is for people to
metabolize that
we have these institutionally and
structurally racist structures.
And I think, to be honest, a couple of
years ago it was a non-argument, you
know, so and you know, these are some of
the retorts to the non-argument.
We're not as bad as America.
All lives matter. Black lives don't just
matter, all lives matter.
If the percentage of the UK populace,
according to the 2011 census, is 14% are
come are made up from a BAME background
and they're only 4% outcome of black
background, then actually having a wider
representation higher education of 13%
is not so bad.
Now, I guess the juxtaposition
to this is that
within the UK we have a migration every
year of around a million students around
the UK.
And since 2003, we've seen numbers very
many increase in terms of number of
black and ethnic minority people going
to university. Now, of that million
students
as of 2015, just over half of that, just
over half of that are now from black and
ethnic minority backgrounds.
2/3 of that half will go on to
postgraduate study
and then we're seeing that chasm, that
slippage in the pipeline, which has been
really, really huge. So, in other words
black people are applying and Asian and
minority ethnic are applying for PhD
studentships, but as we know 30,000
PhD studentships were awarded
in 2018-2019
and only 30 were awarded to black
Caribbean students. So, that's out of
30,000. And that was part of the kind of
groundbreaking research that was led by
Paulette Williams of Leading Roots,
which I was fortunate enough to be a
part of
with Chantel
Lewis and Sukhi Bath.
And there's some really kind of
interesting
tenants around that, because when we
presented that research to OfS, there
was a reluctance to accept that
information's made inaccessible. There
aren't opportunities for BAME people to
progress throughout the academy. And
actually, we have these inherent
structures that in many ways have been
designed to ensure that black and ethnic
minority people don't progress
throughout the academy. And you know, I
myself don't have a benign own
with statistics and numbers, but very
often I'm in a situation where I have to
paint the picture, you know, I have this
canvas and I have to illustrate to
people just how bad things really are
just to get a perspective of where we
need to be going.
So, 20,000 professors in the UK, or just
over 20,000 professors in the UK.
15 and 1/2 thousand are white male.
4 and 1/2 thousand are white women.
And 35 are black women.
And you have a further
90 that are black men.
So, we're talking about less than 1% of
the professoriate in the UK
are black.
And when you bear in mind the migration
of uh
BAME people in higher education, you
would think the numbers would actually
be more than that because a significant
amount go on to postgraduate study.
Now, the thing that I always kind of
find interesting is when we look at
career trajectory, career um
trajectories, one of the things that's
always really interesting is marrying
these trajectories against the
intersection.
So, for example, if you're a woman of
color,
um
what would your salary earnings be if
you had the same qualification, same
skill set, same publication rate in
comparison to your white counterpart?
Now, if we just take the Russell Group
as an example, I was fortunate enough to
do a study with the BBC in 2018 where we
um undertook a study of
the pay differentials between academics
um by ethnicity within the Russell
Group.
So, the average salary for a white
academic in the Russell Group is 52,000
pounds.
The average salary for a black academic
in the Russell Group is 38,000 pounds.
And the average salary from anyone from
an Arab background in the academy is
32,000 pounds. So, we're looking at a
differential of £14,000.
Even though
many uh BAME academics will be as
qualified, will be as capable, will have
met the criteria, but it's about the
structures that are interwoven within
our progressive um
and in many respects um discriminatory
and systemic cultures within the
academy.
And so, like I said, it does become
really important to think of those
numbers because I guess
we have we're we're kind of live on this
carousel of numbers. There's lots of
numbers and statistics flying around.
But the actual only narrative that
matters
is that BAME people are significantly
disadvantaged in the academy
because of the color of their skin.
And the centrality of whiteness
makes it an issue for people of color
to be subjugated and to be disadvantaged
in this way.
Now, for me,
I always say we can engage in mature
debates about this. Um and mature
debates about this from in my opinion
don't involve statistics. I should never
have to really paint out statistics. In
other words, if a person of color says
that they are experiencing racism, why
do we neutralize or challenge or
or question
that experience?
The Meghan Markle interview, for
example.
There's an irony lost. There's no irony
lost on any person of color that a white
middle-class man would question
whether a woman of color has encountered
racism or not. In fact, not question,
would abstractly deny that that person
has encountered racism.
Would make a claim that actually
they have spoken about how racism among
with along with other compounding
factors
was a factor in potentially engaging in
suicidal thought
or change of
state.
But, interestingly, the centrality of
whiteness allows white people to always
question
um or neutralize the experiences
of people of color when it comes to
experiencing racism. So, when we think
about how people talk about racism,
um there is kind of this idea of And
again, I always come back to the
rejection of the idea that people are
encountering racism.
They're playing the race card. It's got
nothing to do with race.
I think you're being slightly
hypersensitive.
We live in a color-blind society, you
know, where we're postmodern. We we we
we're not living in a racialized society
anymore. I think sometimes people just
look for race
racism in anything.
You know, and it's really interesting
because I guess
you know, the paradox to that is that
when we're talking about the white
working class, we're not looking for
race in that.
And what's interesting is the white
working class as a narrative is
extremely important.
And it occupies the center ground
on its own because of its level of
importance, and rightly so. When we talk
about race, race has always been on the
periphery.
And the minute it occupies political
center,
we then have to compromise that
and balance it by saying, "What about
the white working class?"
Now, it's this idea that they both can't
go hand in hand.
Um and I find that really interesting
because one is clearly positioned as
more important than the other, but it's
this kind of again neutralization of um
racism in that it shouldn't be a
priority issue. Now, when we think of
how people navigate
um racism on an everyday basis,
this is the reality of what it is. Most
people, if not all people who negotiate
racism,
they're not thriving, they're surviving.
They're trying to survive in
an institutionally and structurally
racist society.
Now, I think that becomes really
important in all of that.
I am yet to meet a person of color in my
35 years of life who has ever said to
me, "I want to encounter racism."
So, you know, it's a birthright almost
if you want to if you want to look at it
like that. You are a person of color,
you come out of the womb, and you can
almost guarantee that you will
experience some form of racism. If
you're fortunate, maybe once. Um if
you're unfortunate, it'll be every
single day of your life, and for many
people it is. The argument should be you
shouldn't even have to experience it in
the first place.
Once is bad enough. Once is as bad as a
million times.
But, it then becomes beholden on white
people
to think about how we reconceptualize
allyship and anti-racist endeavor. And
for me, a huge part of that is thinking
about how we disrupt patterns of racism,
how we disrupt complicities in racism,
and how we look to center the voices of
um
ethnic minority people, people of color.
That becomes hugely, hugely important
because very often people of color don't
occupy spaces and they do don't have
equal agency in being able to challenge
instances of racism. So, it's about how
we It's not so much Yes, you can talk
about the giving up of privilege, but I
think there's a central argument to how
people use privilege.
And how they use it to disrupt
cycles
of racial discrimination in favor of
creating an intersectionally egalitarian
equal space. And that for me becomes
hugely important.
I just want to kind of finish on one
thing. I think
when we think about race and racism,
there is a huge underestimation of
the impact this has on people's
psychological well-being.
Um
I I have interviewed I think over 400
people, people of color,
over 5-year period
and doing a lot of work on race
and working a lot in terms of around
race and mental health.
And what's always really interesting is
the strategies people use to get through
a day at work.
And what I always say is work doesn't
exhaust me, it's the circumnavigating of
the landmines
that exist in relation to racism. You
know, I'm always not too far from
walking on this landmine of racism. So,
an example of this might be the racial
microaggression.
An example of this may be
watching your white counterparts
progress whilst you have the same
experience, the same qualifications, the
same levels of competence, but you're
not progressing in the same way.
It's watching your voice be in a
dominant white space and not having that
having that voice heard or acknowledged,
but having your white counterpart say
the same thing and have that
acknowledged as gospel.
And that is a is a that is a potent
thing.
The reason why I kind of I I provide
that prelude to go into
a a context is because I think that
I've interviewed people from across many
subject disciplines.
And you know, even when we think about
this particular person I interviewed was
from a STEM background.
And when we think about, you know,
physics or you know, science,
technology, engineering, mathematics,
there are there's a really interesting
narrative around the fact that there are
not a lot of BAME people in that
particular academic discipline.
Actually, if you was to break it down by
percentage, there are more BAME people
that study STEM STEM subjects, that go
on from A-level and go on to higher
education and through to postgraduate,
than there are in any other academic
discipline. I I commonly there's this
thought that most BAME people reside in
social sciences. They don't actually
reside in STEM subjects. And what
becomes really interesting is the lack
of proliferation of those individuals at
higher levels. So, for example, there is
um in in all of the subject disciplines,
there are more BAME students with PhDs
in STEM subjects than they are in any
other discipline. Now,
um traditionally people would presume
straight away that actually they'd be
social sciences, but it isn't. It's
actually in STEM subjects.
But, where are those um STEM academics?
Why can you have situations where people
are qualified,
you know, capably, have published, um
have brought in funding, but they're
still not in academic tenure posts,
permanent posts. Why does that happen?
You know, I would I can make a very
strong argument that it's structures in
place. It's how
um
STEM as a subject, and the social
sciences might add, define excellence.
And that defining of excellence is very,
very narrow. And actually, what it does
is it recognizes
um excellence through one particular
lens. And that particular lens is
whiteness. And that completely obscures
the idea that people of color could be
as capable as their white counterparts
because the perception is the best gets
to the top. And the best is defined as
being
white physicians, you know, white white
um engineers. It's And it's it's it's
it's symptomatic of the sector. But, I
think what's important is how we disrupt
that. It's how we disrupt that. I don't
think it's beyond reproach that we could
redismantle this and create a really
fair and equal space.
One of the stories I was going to tell
um again was someone that had a PhD in
physics at a
really well-respected university.
And they spoke about this idea of um
every day when they go to work, they
apply their makeup twice.
So, they said to me, "Jason, like I know
you you love music." So, I was like,
"Yeah, well, yeah, everyone I think
everyone knows that."
And they were like, "And I know you like
R.E.M." So, I was like, "Yeah." They
were like, "Do you know the song called
Imitation of Life?"
So, I said, "Yeah." I said, "You know
that line in it, 'No one can see me
cry'?" So, I was like, "Yeah, yeah, I I
know that line." And they were like,
"Well, basically, I apply my makeup in
the morning.
I go in. I know I'm going to encounter
racism.
Invariably, I always encounter it. I go
into the toilet. I cry. I get it out of
my system. I lock myself in, and no one
can see me cry.
I'm sat on the toilet seat,
and I'm reapplying my makeup in this
small room mirror.
That's my armor. I come back out. I take
a deep breath
to engage in this process again.
And this happens two or three times a
week, and it has done for 7 years.
Now,
that particular individual, for all of
their,
you know, the accolades they've had, the
institutions they studied at, for their
absolute excellence in the area of
physics,
um, they don't work in the academy
anymore, because there was something
they couldn't do
every day. And this person's 31 years
old. You know, you could make an
argument their career hasn't even begun.
In terms of, we know the longevity of
academic careers, you know, 60 and
beyond. But they've left the academy
with all of that promise. And we can't
afford
to lose some of the best talents in
academia across any subject discipline,
who do come from BAME backgrounds,
equally as much as people come from
white backgrounds. We can't afford to
lose these types of individuals we need
in the academy.
Universities are always positioned as a
microcosm of society. What we need to
ensure is that
our institutions, our higher education
institutions, are reflective of the
multicultural, multi-ethnic society that
we reside in. Because presently, they
don't. And that's across all of
society's major institutions. But higher
education is one of those institutions,
and we all need to think about how we
can move this forward. Now, I'm an
eternal optimist, and I've always
believed that we can change this. But to
change it, there has to be a creation of
hearts and minds that are aligned. And I
think we're
at a really critical juncture in our
race relations history history. Not only
nationally, but globally. And I think
this is a really seminal time for us to
go beyond being kind of twitching
fingers and be this collective fist that
really looks to penetrate the walls of
structural inequality, not just in
relation to racism,
even though that's what I'm talking
about today, intersectionally.
You know, we're living in a university
culture where a sexual harassment, as an
example, has become normative.
To the To the extent that reporting
procedures at universities, to be
honest, facilitate
men to behave inappropriately.
And in a way where there is no
punishment for that.
So, it's about thinking about, you know,
how we challenge all of these structures
to ensure that we're creating a space
where all people feel safe, a sense of
belonging, a sense of being heard, and
really a sense of um connectedness that
comes from a recognizing that we are all
different, and we embrace that
difference and use it as a strength to
mobilize
um what could be an intellectually and
multiculturally stimulating space.
It's always an absolute pleasure to um
have opportunities like this. Um I don't
proclaim to know everything. I don't,
far from it. Um the only thing I try and
do is to try and mobilize change with a
collective of good people. And I feel
like today I'm in really good company,
and um
I think, in my humble opinion, that as
an institution, to have people like Alex
at the fore, leading work like this, is
you you are unbelievably lucky, in my
opinion. But Alex is a woman of color,
and the labor that women of color
exhaust during this endeavor is wrong.
And I say it's wrong because it's a
collective endeavor.
Alex should be supported in doing this.
You know, the burden of this work always
falls on women of color, and I think
it's important for all of us, including
men of color, who profit who have who
have profited also from the work of
women of color, to support um in doing
this work as collective endeavor.
So, Alex, thank you so much for having
me here. Honestly, you're amazing, and I
just feel really privileged to be here,
so thank you so much.
Oh,
that was really touching. Thank you.
Thank you so much for that. It was very
sobering. Uh
but, you know, I think we always have to
hear these things, even though they're
unpleasant, because otherwise, like, if
you don't know, how can you change?
Um I have so many questions for you, and
I can see questions coming in. So, I
thought I would start and ask one of my
questions first, cuz, you know, as the
host, I get that luxury.
So,
there's kind of several things you
touched on that
hopefully I'll be able to come back to
some of my questions, but
you just now spoke about the fact that a
lot of the time the burden for doing
this extra work does fall on people of
color. And particularly pushing forward
the work on racism,
we do tend to drive a lot of that,
because, you know, we have to. Um
So, my question is basically
about yourself. Like, do you feel like
this burden gets put on you a lot? Um
obviously, in your job as, you know, an
expert on racism, I'm I know you work
with lots of universities on their
approach to racism, but like,
do you feel this burden yourself to like
try and make the change? And like, how
do you handle that? Like, how do you not
get overwhelmed by it? Because sometimes
it can get like a it's a lot, right?
Yeah, no, thank you so much. That's a
great question. I mean, it's a weird
situation I I guess for me because um
I have my friends all joke like you
you'll never meet a more reluctant
academic purely because like when I you
know, it wasn't that long ago that I was
teaching physical education um
and 8 years ago, you know, I was saying
this to a friend the other day, you
know, I had when I was doing my PhD and
working full-time, I had weekend jobs at
Tesco and Sainsbury's and was cleaning
toilets. So, I never thought I'd ever be
in a position where I would then now be
an associate professor and an executive
um a deputy executive dean that leads
this this work in my institution.
Um
I think one thing that that um helps is
um
I know change is really slow,
but I I I feel like something is
happening.
And that in itself it there there's an
intrinsic motivation there um because
you kind of feel like you have to do a
bit now. I guess I never asked to be in
a position of um
responsibility in terms of leading this
agenda forward or being part of an
amazing generation of academics that
have done that.
But I I I think the most important thing
is what you do with that responsibility
and I think that it's a privilege to be
in that position where you can advance
change.
I think the most important thing is how
you do it. Who do you bring along with
you?
How do you ensure that all voices are
heard? How do you ensure that uh people
are mobilized
to
to cultivate and to change things in a
way that isn't exploitative or
exhaustive of people of color,
particularly women of color.
And as a black man, I'm keenly aware
that there are privileges that I have
over women of color
that um afford me unfair privileges.
And it's really thinking about how I
challenge and reflect reflect on that
all the time and my positionality
becomes important now.
So, for me,
you know, the great thing about being a
school teacher is that everything was
about practice. You know, the theory of
something and the practice of something.
And the absence of that in higher
education is a really interesting thing.
So, I think people are very good at
theorizing things, but not always very
good at the practical element of it.
Because the theorizing is kind of easy
in some respects. The doing is
difficult, and the doing is what's
always been it placed on women of color,
people of color. It's always the
burden's been on them to do the doing.
And I think um a big part of doing that
work is is recognizing it's going to be
difficult. I I think
you know, thank God I think I've got a
good temperament for it, which helps.
But I also know because of the amount of
people I've interviewed what it's done
to them over a 10, 20, 30, 40-year
period. And so, I'd always made a
conscious decision that in a couple of
years time, in 4 years time my daughter
will be 18. And I've always made a
decision that at that point it'd be a
good time to call it a day because I
don't want it to consume me in the way
it's consumed other people. And also,
because there's a generation of amazing
people coming through that are doing
amazing things. And it's about creating
space for people to take that charge
forward and to really kind of penetrate
and disrupt racism through new guises,
new interventions, new forms, uh new
instruments of anti-racism. And and I
think that's really important. So, the
thing I always know is that um
you know, you're keeping the seat warm
for someone, and someone else will take
over, and then they'll do it better, and
then the next person will come and
they'll do it better. But what I when I
say the word better, better means a
collective endeavor, not just people of
color trying to extricate themselves
from a structure of supremacy that they
never created in the first place.
Thank you. Yeah.
Um
boy.
Sorry. It's just like this whole
conversation is just like I have
so many things that I want to say and
it's like, oh
um
Alex, please honest like please say it.
I think like, you know, these these
things um
I I want to hear what you have to say
and I think your experience as a woman
of color would be very different to
mine. So, please I personally I would
love to hear what you have to say.
Well,
one of the things that
I feel
it's like a tricky line with this. It's
like on the one hand,
as people who are, you know, the the
victims in the system,
you don't want to have to be doing all
the work yourself, but then I think
there's this other side of it where you
also don't want the people who benefit
from the system to be making the
decisions and to be saying, "Oh, this is
how we're going to change."
So, I feel like one thing I keep
encountering is actually I feel like I'd
like to hear your opinion on it is
in a lot of the discussions I have, I
keep saying, "So, why don't we pay
people for this work?
Why don't we pay people for the work so
that,
you know, even if you're suffering from
the effects of structural racism, if
we're asking you to do work to try and
change it, the least we can do is
acknowledge that it's work and pay you.
And like,
do you have a thought on payment for
doing things like EDI work?"
Yeah, I I think what's really
interesting is um people don't get paid
for EDI work and that in it's I I I my
belief is
um I personally I'm not motivated by
money, but I think in life when anybody
pays for something, there's a valuing of
it. There's a valuing If we go to the
shop right now and we spend, I don't
know,
five bucks on a on a on a pair of shoes,
it's because we value it, you know, you
know, the value comes in the fact that
it's something that one wants, right?
And
I think
that EDI work in higher education
institutions and society more generally
isn't valued. It's seen as goodwill.
Mhm. And because of that, people don't
recognize the currency and the value in
that. Because I think
for a lot of white people, it's an
add-on. It's not something that's
particularly important because the
challenging or the mobilization of EDI
and recognizing it by by physically
underpinning it
means that it's going to disrupt a
culture in a space,
an unequal space that in all in in all
honesty, white people do profit from.
They gain from being in that unequal
space. Um
you know, if there are a lot of white
people, if everything became equal
tomorrow,
I think I think I think they would
suffer.
They would they would suffer because I
think for people of color,
they have to work twice as hard
to occupy space. And part of that is the
expectation that they should be doing
EDI work. And because they're a person
of color
or because they're within the
intersection, you're so you're
passionate about shouldn't be paid to do
your passion.
You know, and and universities and
people exploit that. And I always feel
that when people are offering a service,
something that is of currency to an
institution, that they should be paid
for it. And what we've observed is, like
I said, the majority of this work is
done by women of color and they've never
been paid for it and they're not
remunerated for it fiscally or
reputationally. And when it comes to
progressing through our institution,
uh or
when you look at the criteria to get uh
promoted, you know, the university has
kind of allocated them time being EDI to
do EDI work. But when it comes to
promotion and you talk about
citizenship, universities don't include
that within their promotion criteria.
So it's it's thankless is a thankless
task that isn't remunerated, isn't
rewarded, takes up a lot of time, and
actually moves away from the currency
that universities um
that universities reward, which often
white people are in a position to profit
from, which is research,
you know, bringing research grants and
working with part research teams. Now,
for most
people of color, they don't have access
to those types of networks. One, because
of how these spaces work. And two,
because the whole time they're spending
doing EDI stuff.
Not being remunerated for. So, I always
think institutions should do that. They
have the money to do it. But, what
they're doing is
is they're basically to to to go all
South London, they're taking liberties.
That's what they're doing. They're
taking liberties. And they know they're
doing it. And they know that they can
threaten people with employment not
doing it. And, you know, along a flawed
workload model, they could tell they can
come around and say things like, within
this 550 hours, you actually have time
within that. You have You have allocated
time to do that. Which
which we all know is tosh. It does
that that doesn't work like that. And if
that's the case, why are people of color
always burdened with so many
administrative duties
um and tasks in comparison to their
white counterparts at the same grade and
at the same level.
Now,
if someone can answer me those
questions, that's great. But, I I feel
like I feel like there is no answer
that someone can give me that I'd be
willing to listen to. Because I've not
only have I seen it, I've experienced it
myself.
So, and that is the one of the biggest
criticisms that many people of color
said, I'm on the same pay grade same,
but I seem to have more marking, more
administrative responsibilities. And
it's all of these things. And I think
it's convenient for people to obscure
that from discussions and to say, "Well,
it's EDI work, you know. We're giving
you agency by you doing it. You know,
you shouldn't You know, you want You
want to dismantle racial inequality. You
shouldn't be paid to do that."
You know, and then the then the
gaslighting happens.
Right. Okay. So, as a person of color
who's encountering racism,
I didn't I didn't create this. I didn't
ask to encounter racism. But, you want
me to solve the problem. You also want
me to do the work. And you want me to be
gracious about it and not say anything
about it as well. Like it's it's the
most ridiculous
system, and I don't want to curse, but
it's the most ridiculous system one one
could imagine.
And the thing is, when we apply it to
other intersections, for example, like
gender, gender work within higher
education institutions is often fiscally
rewarded.
Case in point, Athena SWAN.
Athena SWAN is an intervention that is
funded and institutions provide
contributions in kind or match funding
to support that endeavor. Now, when we
think about um who Athena SWAN has
benefited benefited, it's a fantastic
intervention. But let's be specific
about who it's benefited. It's benefited
white middle-class women. It hasn't
benefited white working-class women, and
it damn sure hasn't benefited women of
color.
So, let's let's be accurate when we're
talking about that. And you know, we
know that from the statistics in terms
of pay.
And the huge pay differentials between
um
white middle-class women and women of
color, and white working-class women as
well.
Thank you. You said a lot of things that
rang very true.
Um I'm going to delve into the questions
so that people feel like I'm asking
their questions as well, and not just my
own. Um
So, here's a question that I think ties
in really nicely with what we've just
been talking about, and it's
how do people who aren't empowered in
the current system
help to deconstruct?
Like how
how can we try and
change things, I guess?
I I think the you know, I think it comes
back to E-word, educating yourself.
Um I think there are a lot of dynamics
around gender that I've spent the best
part of a decade trying to understand
and understand how my presence as a male
impacts those factors, particularly
along the intersection. I think
educating oneself is really important. I
think getting comfortable with the
uncomfortable is a really important
thing.
And I think it's the recognizing of
privilege. You know, you can we can we
can all learn. I think it's it's kind of
going there's there's you know, there's
these kind of in becoming anti-racist
there's these kind of zones of
proximity. There's the There's the the
fear zone.
There's a zone of comfort.
And then there's a zone of understanding
and implementation. And I think for a
lot of people
fear zone is almost a reluctance to
accept racism exists. That comfort zone
is you're challenging aspects of of you
you understand that racism exists but
you're not doing enough to challenge it
and disrupt it. When you get into that
third zone
when you get into that third zone, that
becomes really really important because
then you learn that understanding of
okay, how do I disrupt these spaces? How
do I challenge racism? How do I engage
in white allyship that doesn't center me
as a white person centers people of
color. I'm still able to use my
privilege to disrupt
acts of racism or racial microaggression
towards my colleague of color.
Um and all of that for me comes from
educating. And also there's a patience
on the other side of that that needs to
recognize that people are at different
stages of this learning journey and
people will arrive at particular types
of understandings around race and racism
at different times. Um and one thing I
would say with people of color, which
has been time immemorial, that they've
always been patient and they've always
been, you know, very gracious because to
engage in racist encounters every day
and to show restraint really shows the
temperament you need to negotiate those
situations. And that's a really
difficult thing amongst all the other
intersections that they may be managing.
So for me, it's about um
how we reconceptualize white allyship.
The murder of George Floyd has allowed
us to have a brief pause, reflexive
pause, about how we engage in white
allyship. And it's to recognize that the
work of being a white ally can't be
seasonal. There can't be a seasonal
approach. So, in other words,
uh do you know what? Summer's looking
good. I'm going to take the summer off.
I I I I I I'll take it I'll probably
take off autumn, but then I I I'll get
back on it in winter and and and
probably spring. You know, it's it's got
to it's got to be all four seasons
because the other side of that is that
people of color don't have the luxury of
saying, "Do you know what? I don't feel
like encountering racism this season.
I'll take I'll take it I'll take it
off." And then it's part of their lived
existence. So, being on that journey is
literally kind of engaging in a
ride-or-die capacity. You know, you you
you've got to be with that person all
the time. And it's really really When I
say all the time, I mean it
metaphorically in terms of being in
those spaces and disrupting it and
learning what white allyship is, not
through asking a person of color, "What
can I do?" but by observing, by
educating, by reading. Once you've
engaged in that process, then you can
speak to a person of color and say, "How
else can I be of support?"
And I think it comes from that basis of
education which forms a base of
understanding and acknowledges that as a
white person, you're willing to do the
work rather than ask and place more
labor on people of color and say,
"What can I what what can I do to help?"
Cuz that that is a really short circuit
solution. And it's quite lazy. It's lazy
anti-racism, to be honest. Um
it's about educating oneself. You know,
in terms of um sexism, you know, I don't
go to women and say to women, "What can
we do?
What can men do to help?" You know, I I
I try and do my education first, think
about how men, you know, behave in ways
that are completely abhorrent.
And then I do that work. I sit with that
uncomfortability.
I learn. And then I ask from a position
of understanding and knowledge, "What
can I do
to disrupt male patriarchy?"
And and and I and I use that as an
example because I I always try and talk
with people, not at people.
Thank you.
Um so, we've got so many questions. I'm
trying to pick one.
Um
Uh sorry, it's it's really stressful.
So, I saw one that
isn't really a question, but I kind of
want to say it. And someone has said
here, "What about physics?" And
so, number one, I'm not entirely sure
what they're asking about physics.
But, I'm going to interpret it how I
want to interpret it.
Um
and what I want to say is that whilst
Jason is an expert in sociology and
racism, you know, I think it's fair to
say you're not an expert in physics.
And you don't work in the physics
department.
My my my two Fs in science ain't going
to help you on this one.
Well, I just wanted to briefly talk
about
like what I think about physics. And
from looking around, for instance,
Oxford's physics department, it is
predominantly white. And I think, coming
back to what Jason says,
like it's not a question of people of
color not having qualifications or not
being good enough to be in the
department. There's clearly other
factors at work, and they are structural
racism.
One of the things that I would
personally like to see more in our
department is
more people of color being invited for
talks, occupying more space in the
department. Like, we obviously can't
overnight just hire loads of people of
As much as I would like, um it's not
going to happen.
But, I if the For me, the thing I would
really like to see from people in the
department is holding other people
accountable because
it's a cultural thing as much as it is a
structural thing. Like, every single
thing that we let go, every single
little instance that you might observe
as a white person, which you think, "Oh,
that wasn't okay." It's up to you to use
your privilege to call people out and
hold people accountable and to make the
environment better for people because
it's not just a case of not having
people
of color in the department. It's the
fact that like perhaps the environment
isn't pleasant and this again goes back
to something that you said that
you know, sometimes you're there, you're
trying your hardest and you're dealing
with the microaggressions or just like
the outright racism and we need our
white allies to step up and say, "No,
you don't have to deal with this. I will
tell this person why they're wrong and I
will hold them accountable and I will
make the complaint."
So, even though this person uh
asked a question that I don't really
understand what the question was, I
think I've answered it.
Right. All right.
Sorry. It's We're supposed to be hearing
from you, not from me.
No, no, Alex, it's brilliant.
Um
Okay, this is an interesting one. Um
As So, the the question is if you're a
as a white passing but still
person who would be categorized as BAME,
do you personally believe that if you're
white passing you still experience acts
of systemic racism in your employment or
is there a different form of racism that
white passing but people of color
experience?
I think that's a great question. I mean
probably the obvious answer is that
there is a proximity to whiteness and
based on how colorism works and how
colonialism works, that there is a there
are preferences.
Um but I think that is also it is
important that we don't neutralize the
experiences of people included white
passing. Um and the reason why I say
that is because they would have had to
encounter
uh being biracial
and really trying to identify space of
belonging in a way that actually in some
cases maybe people who are
black black passing if that's a term, um
wouldn't have to because there's that
there's that kind of there's that kind
of sense of in in in some respects being
nomadic, you know, not having a place
where you belong because, you know, in
some respects white people kind of look
at you and can think
there's something slightly different
about you which can kind of really
facilitate this really bizarre
fetishization, you know, there's an
exoticism that you know all these kind
of
artistic words which just
yeah, I can only describe with a sound.
Like um you know, and it's not to you
know, if I if I'm being absolutely
honest, I think black women
um
more than any other race encounter
racism in a way that is very very unique
and hostile.
Um
so you know, it's not about hierarchy of
experience, but it's important to say
that
cuz I think the absence of not saying
that is is one quite insensitive and
it's quite a truce to not acknowledge
some of that. But I do think that there
is this idea that people who are white
passing don't experience racism in the
same way and I think that we need to be
careful of doing that. We need to be
careful of
of segregating and we don't want to
homogenize, but we also don't want to
suggest that, you know, people that
there there's almost like a
a a level of racial experience. I think
it's very unique to the individual and I
think that we need to be careful of
suggesting that because someone is white
passing or has a proximity to whiteness,
they somehow encounter less racism, you
know,
I try not to speak
about
um
being another I try not to speak for
someone's shoes I haven't been in
before. I don't know what it's like to
be in that situation. Um and I would
imagine um having a dad that is biracial
that actually there are well I know I
know for a fact there are a lot of
issues in terms of
a sense of non-belonging
from both sides. So, I think that's kind
of really important to acknowledge that
and to recognize that there is something
in political blackness as a movement.
And that movement is inclusive of
people of color.
And, you know, a pro you know,
being white passing, it one of those
terms that I I never really like because
I think that can actually be a
neutralizer in terms of how someone
experiences racism. And I say that
because basically because they may be
perceived as white passing,
for that individual, they may feel in
certain spaces that I can't talk about
being racialized.
And and and that is stifling.
That is stifling, and I think people of
color who encounter racism should always
be given a platform to talk about their
racialized experiences with society and
all of us recognizing that people
experience racism in many different ways
in terms of people of color. So, I think
that's really important. But, I also
caveat that by saying, you know,
black women in particular do encounter
racism in a very violent, epistemic, and
unique way that I don't actually think
is comparable.
And and I think that's important to say.
That was yeah, a really great answer. I
felt very spoken to through a lot of
that answer
cuz this is definitely something that I
think I encounter
uh cuz I don't really look
that brown, I guess.
So,
here's a question that I find
interesting to think about. Um
Do you think that affirmative action or
something similar is a tool that
universities in the UK should implement
having seen the effects of it in the US?
I actually have to say something really
funny. As soon as you said affirmative,
I was like
I was just like just stop the just stop
the question right there. One If if
there is one thing I would bring into
the UK, it would be affirmative action.
And we don't have it. The our equivalent
of affirmative action is positive
action. And I can't think of a
legislation that we make more poor use
of than that.
If if positive action was used
effectively in higher education, there
is a lot we could do to diversify the
space and create a more equal space, but
we don't. We use it selectively and
there's an ambiguity with it that is
applied by a lot of
white senior leaders
um that it in fact doesn't it doesn't
benefit people of color.
And they could use it to do that. You
know, you can have BAME PhD
studentships. You can have
um
you know
selection panels or shortlist panels
like where you make a conscious effort
to have a better rep BAME representation
not only on the on the recruitment
panels, but also on the shortlisting.
There are things that you can do and we
don't utilize
uh positive action enough, but if I
personally had my own way,
um I would have affirmative action. I I
I would think this is probably the most
arrogant thing I've ever said and I'm
not an arrogant person, but I would be
one of the biggest advocates
um in higher education for affirmative
action. I I think that is the way to go.
I think sometimes there are times where
to accelerate change, you have to
you have to
force the issue on certain things.
And I would do that because
the disaggregation that people of color
face in the academy in terms of pay,
progression, wider representation
being in positions of leadership, that
is never going to change if we sit with
the current system we've got now. It
will be like that in 10 years time. And
that's not me being pessimistic. Things
will improve, but they're only they're
only as effective as the type of
leaderships, type of leaders you have,
types of institutions you have, types of
people that are incumbent, the types of
custodians
of the academy that reside within it,
the gatekeepers to knowledge. You know,
it's it's about changing all of that.
And the only way to really do it,
because there is a reluctance
by a lot of white people to give up that
privilege, is is to is to in some
respects, I wouldn't say forcibly, but
when you're talking about affirmative
action, there is something that is quite
forcible about it.
And and I think that is an intervention
that is needed in the UK.
Otherwise, we're going to
there'll be 101 culture reviews,
there'll be 101 race reports. You know,
there'll be
we'll be talking about the first report
not 22 years later, 40 years later, and
still using the same terms. We made
fragile gains since the offering of that
report. And I don't want us to use that
kind of lexicon anymore. I want us to
actually make tangible structural
changes, and I do think affirmative
action will facilitate that
massively.
Yeah. I I've always felt that part of
the reason there's such a pushback to
the idea of having affirmative action in
the UK is not it's
also ties into our like weird class
system.
I feel like it's not just
there's like the class elements, and
then like the racism elements, and then
obviously like the sexism, and anything
else that ties into it. Um
I mean, I would I would have to be
honest, I would apply it across the
intersection. I wouldn't I wouldn't I
wouldn't just advocate that for race.
I'd apply that across the intersection,
you know, um
but yeah, I mean, I would particularly
focus on race because our major
institutions are pretty much all
entirely white. So,
for obvious reasons, um I'm I'm not
white, so I would I would I
I would I would push for that.
Yeah, that's right.
Yeah, sorry.
Yeah.
Um there's a question here that I really
want to ask because even though it's a
slight deviation, it actually ties into
something that I've been hearing a lot
about. Do you think the term BAME can be
damaging?
Because you're essentially lumping
together all non-white people and
treating them equally. And when you do
things like break down the statistics,
for instance, you could say, "Oh, 40% of
our staff are BAME, but actually only 1%
is black." And so,
what are your thoughts on catchall terms
like BAME, like BIPOC, for instance?
That's a
Yeah. I I I think catchall terms like
BAME are hugely problematic. And in
every
piece of writing I've ever done, I've
always had to put a footnote saying that
this term is problematic. Um, but in
policy documents and in policy
interventions, it's still the term that
um
the government prefers to use. And there
hasn't been anything in parliamentary
spaces in Whitehall to suggest that that
is going to change anytime soon. I mean,
the operative word being Whitehall.
Um, so I I think um
the homogenizing of of ethnic minorities
is problematic, which is why I prefer
terms like either just saying black and
minority ethnic people or people of
color. Um, and
there is a homogenizing of those
experiences, which always paints a
picture that, you know, amongst black
and ethnic minority people or BAME
people, their outcomes aren't as bad as
they suggest.
Because there's that grouping. But when
you kind of separate the kind of
the fat from the strain,
what what you do what you do see is that
within those particular groups, they
experience things very very differently.
So, for example, how the comparison is
drawn between black African and black
Caribbean, there's there's huge distinct
profiles in terms of
um
academic um outcomes. When we think
amongst um South Asian communities and
we think particularly around, you know,
Indian, Bangladeshi, and Pakistani,
between Bangladeshi and Pakistani, um
against Indian,
there are huge, you know, Indian, you
know, Pakistani, people from Pakistani
and Bangladeshi backgrounds tend to have
lower um education educational
attainment. But when it's lumped
together, it can present this like a
whole holistic picture. Particularly
when you talk about Asian because then
we're also talking about East Asian,
which can kind of compound that as well.
And then when we talk about people from
um Romany and traveler groups, again,
that's a completely unique experience
because there is still a proximity to
whiteness, but they but individuals from
that diaspora are a racial are a racial
group or an ethnic group. So it's
recognizing kind of the differences and
not using those terms and really moving
beyond the laziness of engaging in that
as a homogeneous activity. It's
recognizing
they're not subtle nuances, they are
quite big nuances between those ethnic
categories. And I think the more we
engage in language that recognizes that,
the better. Otherwise, what we're doing
is subverting everyone's experience to
be the same.
And that isn't the case because,
you know, like I said, of 30,000 PhD
studentships awarded, only 30 were
awarded to black
British Caribbean people. That that is
that is remarkable.
That is remarkable. And by the way, the
number for the amount of black
studentships that were studentships
awarded to black people,
um predominantly from African
backgrounds, is not much more than that.
So it's something like 100.
So you're still talking you're still
talking about a you know, still a
pathetic number out of 30,000 when you
bear in mind that in that particular
year, the majority, you know, two just
over half of the applications, according
to HESA, um because we got a Freedom of
Information act. Over half of the
applications
um, for
black and ethnic minority uh, people
came from black and ethnic minority
people in relation to gaining
studentship, PhD studentship places.
So, even though this information isn't
accessible, black people and ethnic
minorities are still finding ways to
apply for these programs.
But, I mean, if someone can explain to
me why you have that volume of people
applying and only
30 black Caribbeans are deemed worthy
enough to have that over 30,000 people,
uh, I know only is.
Well,
that's yeah, wow.
Those numbers are just awful, right?
They're just
Yeah, and I and the thing is, like I
said, I I mean, I I said I don't have a
benign obsession with numbers. It
probably seems like a like I do, but um,
sadly, to illustrate where we are, very
often you have to, you know, um,
you have to kind of prophesize what
these numbers are because I think, you
know, a lot of people don't have an
understanding of just how bad it is, you
know? But, I also think that by having
these conversations, what we have seen
is a sea section and a change in how we
are conceptualizing and understanding
this context. And I do think as a
result, we are going to see greater
change in the next couple of years. I
think we're beginning to see it now.
You know, the OFS
um, have responded to the broken
pipeline report and as a result, now
there's that huge bid that's kind of
coming out in terms of uh, mobilizing
uh,
black and ethnic minority opportunities
at PGR level, particularly doctoral
level.
Well, um, I feel like that was a slight
a slight optimism for which we can end
our talk on. Um,
so, thank you so much, Jason. This has
been
sobering, but really great to have you
here talking. And I know this is
probably like the first time in the
department anyone's gone into this in
such depth and so I'm really happy that
we could have you here to do it. Um
thank you everyone for attending.
I hope you enjoyed it and we will be
putting it on YouTube when we've had
time. So yeah, thank you so much and I
hope you all have a great day.
Um
And Alex, you're brilliant. Just thank
you so so much and everyone like
literally live well and I hope
everyone's well and much love and take
care everyone.
Thanks so much.
Thanks.